Guide to the Carl Pettersch Papers: Academic Affairs. Office of the Dean of Graduate Studies RG 6.4.0 RG 6.4.0
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Carl Pettersch Papers: Academic Affairs. Office of the Dean of Graduate Studies
1952-1972
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Pettersch, Carl A. (Carl Alfred), 1906-
RG 6.4.0
2.5 Linear Feet, 5 boxes
Carl A. Pettersch was Professor of Social Science 1946-1955, Dean of Graduate Studies 1955-1973, Faculty Emeriti 1973-2003 as Professor of History. This collection comprises the papers of Dr. Pettersch while Dean of Graduate Studies.
2.5 linear feet (5 boxes)
Provenance
These materials were stored in the basement of Old Main with other miscellaneous 1969-1980 era University materials including Alumni Affairs publications. They were transferred to the Archives in Dec. 2008.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Carl Pettersch was a long time member of the WestConn community and served the University in many capacities. Pettersch was Professor of Social Science 1946-1955, Dean of Graduate Studies 1955-1973, and Faculty Emeriti 1973-2003 as Professor of History.
Carl married his wife, Clarissa, a kindergarten teacher, in the 1930s and he obtained his teaching certificate from the University of Detroit. He first taught in Michigan, teaching history, Latin, English literature, and political science. He went on to earn his doctor of education degree from Columbia University and to serve as dean of graduate studies at Western Connecticut State. He retired in 1972. He co-founded Emeritus College at Aquinas College in Grand Rapids and produced a series of more than 200 radio broadcasts for listeners in western Michigan.
His wife Clarissa died in 1991. Carl married Louise Buckley, the widow of his Notre Dame roommate, Louis Buckley. Pettersch and Louise both passed away in 1998. Pettersch was 92.
Sources:
University of Notre Dame - Named Library Collections. [http://www.library.nd.edu/advancement/documents/Pettersch2007.pdf]
Scope and Content Note
Carl A. Pettersch served in many capacities while at WestConn. He was Professor of Social Science from 1946-1955, Dean of Graduate Studies from 1955-1973, and Faculty Emeriti from 1973-2003 as Professor of History. This collection comprises the papers of Dr. Pettersch during his appointment as Dean of Graduate Studies and is arranged into five series: 1. Programs; 2. Syllabi; 3. Studies/Reports; 4. Meetings/Notes and, 5. Miscellaneous. The content of the collection mainly focuses around the development and revision of graduate programs at Western Connecticut State College.
The programs series is mainly comprised of proposals for graduate programs, such as MA English, Sixth Year Teaching Certificate, and Psche Examiner, and the associated correspondence and reviews for those programs.
The Syllabi series includes the syllabi and course outlines for varying numbers of courses offered in each graduate program.
The series of Studies and Reports consists of reports regarding the usefulness and how to execute programs, as well as, how the graduate school and the community interact as well.
The Meetings and Notes Series covers such information as the Minutes of Deans and Directors meetings regarding programs at WCSC and associated initiatives.
The materials in the Miscellaneous series encompases educational newsletters, general correspondence, and proposals for graduate studies initiatives.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Missing Title
Programs
Syllabi
Studies/Reports
Meetings/Notes
Miscellaneous
Related Material
Division of Academic Affairs Records
Correspondence.; Universities and colleges -- Administration.; Sylabi.; Reports.; Minutes.; Western Connecticut State University. Division of Academic Affairs.; Pettersch, Carl A. (Carl Alfred), 1906-
- Programs
  - Graduate Programs, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Extension and Off-Campus Courses, 1952-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - New Programs General Material, 1964-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - New Programs Development and Projections, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - English MA Program, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - English MA Program, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - NWCC/WCSC Criminal Justice Program, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sixth Year Program, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sixth Year Program, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mathematics MA Program, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Guidance Counselor Program, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Psyche Examiner Program, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - History MA Program, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Summer Earth Science Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Westport Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - UCONN/CT State Colleges Co-op, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Summer Session, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - BS in Business Administration Proposal, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Graduate Program Applications, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Syllabi
  - Graduate Course Catalog Orders, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Graduate Course Syllabi Science, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Graduate Course Syllabi Art/Music, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Graduate Course Syllabi Mathematics, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Graduate Course Syllabi Political Science, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Graduate Course Syllabi Social Science, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Graduate Course Syllabi Psychology, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Graduate Course Syllabi History, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Graduate Course Syllabi English, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Graduate Course Syllabi Education, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Psychology Undergraduate Course Oultines, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Studies/Reports
  - Hajj Survey: Arab Speakers in Danbury Area, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Koenker Study: Sixth Year Education Programs, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Koenker Study: Institution Co-op at Graduate Level, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Nelson Report: Teacher Education, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Wilder Study: DSC Role in Community Service, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Emens Report, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - MA in Education Report, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Four Colleges Graduate Committee Report, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Meetings/Notes
  - Four Colleges Graduate Committee, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Evening Meeting Minutes, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Deans and Directors Meetings 1-2, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Deans and Directors Meetings 2-2, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Data and Proposals Re: Income and Tuition, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Graduate Division and Program Missions, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Johansen: Site Planner Materials, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Assistance For Teacher Shortage Areas, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Teacher Certification Regulations, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Teachers Certification Regulations, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - CACE, 1967-1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Community Service Program Newsletter, 1970-1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Commencement Lists and Correspondence, 1952-1963 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Commencement Lists (MS Degree), 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Commencement Lists (MS Degree), 1969 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Commencement Lists, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Commencement Programs, 1953-1968 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Commencement Programs, 1969-1974 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Courses Off Campus, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Graduate Theses Lists, 1957-1973 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Summer Session for School Nurses, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - CCSC New Programs, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - CCSC Proposed program in Education Supervision and Curriculum Development, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 15)